A health insurance claim of ₹4.5 lakh comes.  If
the policy is worth ₹ lakh then this claim should be received
but this claim gets rejected.
Because this policy was not purchased from the right place.
Hello, my name is Ravindra
Singh and today I am going to tell you something
that no insurance company, health
insurance agent or broker will admit.
As important as your health insurance
plan and health insurance company are, equally
important is the decision about where you buy this plan from.
Many people obsess
that I want this plan of HDFC.
This policy of Care is the best.  This plan of Star is
good.  Neema Bupa plan is the
best.  But no one knows
that they should buy this policy directly from the company's
website.
Buy this policy from a broker like Policybazaar or from an agent.
You should stay till the end of this video
because this is not a video.
This is the first video in a series of five videos, by the
end of which it will be
absolutely clear to you what is the best
place to buy health insurance in India.   First of all let
me introduce you to Rahul.
Rahul is tech savvy.  Do all the work online.
He also purchased car insurance online.
So after doing complete research on health insurance, I
purchased the policy directly from the insurance company's website.   I got
my favorite plan and
also got an online discount of ₹3000.  Everything was going well
but after 2 years his father
felt chest pain and had to rush to the hospital at 11:00 pm.  The
doctor recommended that an
emergency heart surgery be performed immediately.   The
claim is filed.  Rahul
signs the pre-authorization form and
hands it over to the TP desk.  Before the approval of the cashless claim,
a query is raised by the insurance company, which
Rahul could not answer.  He did not understand
why these documents were being asked for
and what he had to tell them about it.
He tried to contact the insurance company.  Could
not talk.
He also sent an email but it was an emergency.
Now he had to submit some documents
or answers and due to not submitting them,
this cashless claim was not approved.  He paid ₹35 lakh
from his own pocket and now he has
filed a reimbursement claim in which he does
not know how much money the company will pay and whether it will get
approval or not.  Friends, the second claim
incident is of Mr. Shyam
who bought the same policy for ₹3000 more
from his insurance agent and in the same
way his family also had to face an emergency hospitalization.
Called the time agent of the claim.  The
agent picked up the call at 11:00 pm and he
also came to the hospital the next day.  Shyam says that
not only was his cashless claim approved,
but the
agent also got the claim forms for pre and post hospitalization expenses
submitted by him.  He got that money also.
Same policy, same coverage but
what is the difference in claim experience
in both these situations.  Why?  Because
where we have purchased the policy from matters a
lot.  So friends, in this video
series,
I am going to tell you the pros and cons of all the four methods from
where you buy policies.
In this video I will give you a little outline
but detailed video of every method of every place with
pros and cons is going to come after this.  The first
source is the first way to buy a policy.  You can
buy it directly by visiting the insurance company's website.
Nowadays, the website of every insurance company
is so tech enabled that you
can buy the policy directly.  There is HDFC, Tata
AIG, NVPA, go to any company's website and
buy the policy and there are no medical
complications.  So the
policy will be delivered to you directly within a very short time.  The
biggest advantage of buying a policy directly from the insurance company's website is
that you get some online
discount of 5, 7, 10%.
Because the commissions given to the middleman,
agent or broker do not have to be given to the company.  When
that cost is reduced,
some benefits are passed on directly to the customer.
And what are the disadvantages?
You are alone here.  If you have
purchased the policy directly from the insurance company, then no
one will guide you at the time of claim.
And you may feel that the insurance
company which I considered so supportive and with me at the
time of purchasing the policy is probably
against me now.  She is standing in front of me.
But still many people buy
these policies online directly from the insurance company.
Because it is
very suitable for those who are tech savvy.
Know how to use tech well, how to use apps and websites.
Those who have read the policy wordings very carefully.
He knows every coverage detail.
And most importantly, those who have
time to handle the claim process and all the
documentation, they
buy policies online.  But these are
just a few pros and cons.
Apart from this, there are many other aspects that
you should keep in mind while purchasing a policy online.
If you want the
next video in this series to be on the
pros and cons of buying a policy directly from an insurance company,
then write in the comment section
online.  The
video of the source with the most votes will
appear first.
Another way for you to buy health insurance can be online
brokers.  Policy Bazaar
is the biggest name here.  But apart from this, there are many brokers like Renew Buy,
Insurance Dekho, Tertment
who provide you health insurance policies online.  The
biggest advantage of buying a policy from an online broker is
that you get to see 15 to 20
health insurance companies and their plans on a single platform.
You can compare it with others.
Within 10 to 15 minutes you
also get comparison pricing wise of so many companies.
But the biggest problem in buying a policy from here is
that they work on commission
basis.  All brokers work on a commission basis
and the policy they
recommend to you may
not be the best for you.  The second problem is
regarding their claim support.  When you
call at the time of claim, you do
not get consistent support.  You may be talking to a different executive each time.
But data shows that a lot of people
buy policies from online brokers and this should be done by
those who are buying a policy for the first time.  There
is no medical condition.  It is a straight forward policy.  They
can buy it directly from here.
You will get transparent comparison and
pricing is also competitive.  But these are
also just a few pros and cons.  If
you want the next video to be on online
brokers.  If you
want to understand their pros and cons in detail then
write in the comment section.  The third
method is our traditional method which we have been
using for years.  Buying a
policy from your family insurance agent.  The
same uncle who gave my father his
first LIC policy.  Now they
also deal in health insurance and we will
buy the policy from them only.  But
what is its benefit?  Brother, the trust is already formed.
He is like a member of our family.
Sometimes one has to get admitted to the hospital
, if any claim comes then he personally visits
and also follows up the formalities of all the claims
himself.  But there are some
problems also.  The biggest problem
with them is that they have only one company.
We have to plan for that only.
But we don't want to leave uncle either.
He is a trusted person.  And the other big
problem is that sometimes they try too hard to sell the policy.  There are
expensive policies
or products that I do
n't need to buy at all.  But still
many I would say most of the people
buy this policy from an insurance agent
because it is better for those
who want a trusted person to
handle their claims.
Hand holding during their claims,
guide them and at the same time, those policy
holders who
prefer a personal touch over digital facility, digital convenience,
that someone one on one should guide me,
help me, they
buy the policy directly from their agent in the traditional way.
So if you want me to
discuss in detail the pros and cons of buying a policy from an agent
in the next video, then comment, agent.  The
video of the source with the most comments will be shown first.  The fourth way to
buy a policy is to avail a fee-based
advisory service.  You
pay money to an experienced person and he will
guide you impartially as to
which health insurance plan you should take.
Now he has no interest in commissions.
So the first advantage is that
their advice will be unbiased.  He will
not favor any one company or plan.
But the biggest problem here is
that you will have to pay advisory fees every time, which is
not comfortable for everyone.  And this
amount is also not small.  The advisory fee for one consultation session can range from ₹1000 to ₹
3000, ₹5000, even ₹100.
But still,
buying a policy from here can be beneficial for many people.  Those people who
want to get completely unbiased
advice.  There should not be any sales
pressure.  Policy holders who have
very high coverage.  Sum insured is ₹50 lakh.
Sum insured is Rs 1 crore.
So they must invest in advisory based services.
And along with this,
those policy holders who are confused and do
not know which plan to take
, can also avail this service
for unbiased advice.  But these are also just a few
pros and cons.  Apart from this, there can be many
advantages and disadvantages of this service.
So if you want the next video in this series to be
about the pros and cons of the online advisory channel, then
write online advisory.  I will
definitely make a video on this.  Another thing that
most people notice is that
while buying a health insurance policy, everyone
appears to be your best friend.   If
you visit the website, you will feel that there is no
company in the world friendlier than them.  The
agent is a family member as if
their trust is already built up.
Online brokers also make many promises that
you will not face any problem at the time of claim
and the advisory based service
is good.  Sir, give me the money and take advice.
But their commitments and services become
truly evident when a
health insurance claim is filed
and then the reviews are completely different.  Many
people who
purchased policies directly from the insurance company's website
face delays in deductions and claim approvals because they did
not receive timely support and guidance.   While
purchasing policies from online brokers like Policy Bazaar, there are complaints that
my relationship manager has changed.
I had purchased the policy from someone else.  Every time the
entire story has to be told again for the claim
and then they reply as per their convenience.
If you
buy a policy directly from an insurance agent, the claim service
is good but whether everyone has a good
insurance agent around them or not is also a
problem.
You do get advice at the time of claim from the advisory platform
but it does not have that personal touch.
You will have to pay money every time.  If you
get advice, you won't feel the personal
attention that should be there
in helping with a direct claim.  And
I always say that cheap does
not mean good.
You may get the cheapest health insurance from any source.
But that does
n't mean it's the best.
A small piece of advice or guidance at the time of claim can
lead to rejection of a claim worth lakhs of rupees
or may cause problems or difficulties.
Therefore, in this series of five videos,
today's first video was an introductory
video.  In the upcoming videos, I am going to tell you the detailed pros and cons of each source from
where you can buy the policy.
You can tell me by commenting which video you want first so that by the
end of the series it becomes absolutely clear to you
which is the best source, the best place, the better place to buy your policy
?  Without any regrets and without any
confusion.  If you feel that the
topic of today's video series is interesting for you,
then you can subscribe to the channel
so that
you do not miss the upcoming videos of this series and along with this,
also tell me by commenting
from which place and which source you have purchased the health insurance policy
and whether you have had any claim
experience, if yes then how was it. I would
like to make one last request to you
that if any of your friends, family
colleagues or relatives are
thinking of buying a health insurance plan
or are getting it renewed, then
definitely share the link of this video and this series with them.
One share of yours may
save him from making a big mistake.  Think how much
help they will have.  See you in the next video.
Till then take care.  Jai Hind.